Do you take care about what you wear?
你会在意自己的穿着吗？
Some people are very fashion-conscious, carefully selecting the clothes they buy and how they dress.
有些人十分注重时尚，会精心挑选购买的衣物和穿搭方式。
Fashionistas always want to be seen in the latest designer gear.
时尚达人总是希望身着最新款的设计师单品亮相。
But that trend is changing as retro or vintage clothing is becoming a popular and often cheaper alternative.
但这股潮流正在发生变化，复古服饰逐渐成为一种受欢迎且通常价格更低的选择。
Of course, ‘vintage’ clothing is really second-hand clothing, worn before but given a new lease of life.
当然，“复古”服饰其实就是二手衣物，虽被人穿过，却重焕了生机。
The fashion industry has rebranded this stuff to make it look trendy and possibly give it a higher price tag.
时尚行业为这类衣物重新打造了品牌形象，让它们看起来颇具潮流感，甚至还能卖出更高的价格。
Whereas we may have seen an old faded pair of jeans or a gingham-patterned dress sold at a jumble sale, now there are boutique and pop-up shops dedicated to the stuff.
以前，我们或许会在旧货义卖活动上看到褪色的旧牛仔裤或是方格纹连衣裙，而如今，有不少精品店和快闪店专门售卖这类服饰。
And in the UK, one supermarket chain has started selling second-hand clothes in some of its stores under the brand, Preloved Vintage Wholesale.
在英国，一家连锁超市还在部分门店推出了名为“珍爱复古批发”的二手服装品牌。
Its managing director Steve Lynam told the BBC: "The more people that buy into the circular economy and shop vintage and retro, the bigger impact we will have on climate change."
该品牌的常务董事史蒂夫·莱纳姆在接受BBC采访时表示：“越多的人参与到循环经济中，购买复古服饰，我们对气候变化产生的积极影响就会越大。”
Certainly, buying vintage does prolong the life of clothing. It cuts down on waste and helps to reduce the environmental damage caused by manufacturing new clothes.
毫无疑问，购买复古服饰能延长衣物的使用寿命，减少浪费，还能降低因生产新衣物而造成的环境破坏。
It’s also led to the rise of retro-fashion – items that your mum or dad wore decades ago that now look ‘cool’ again!
这一趋势也带动了复古时尚的崛起——那些几十年前父母辈穿的衣服，如今又重新变得“时髦”起来！
It’s a big thing with younger people and has been helped by the rise of platforms like Depop and Vinted, which sell ‘worn’ clothes online.
复古时尚在年轻人中十分流行，而Depop和Vinted这类线上二手服饰交易平台的兴起，也进一步推动了这股潮流。
Ianina Lucca from Depop told the BBC: “The new generation is… looking to make choices that reduce their impact on the environment, with 77% of Gen Z saying that their biggest environmental concern being that they want their choices to reduce waste.”
Depop平台的亚尼娜·卢卡告诉BBC：“新一代的年轻人正致力于做出能减少自身环境足迹的选择，77%的Z世代表示，他们最关心的环境问题就是希望自己的选择能减少浪费。”
Another popular way of buying old clothes is in a vintage kilo sale.
购买旧衣物的另一种流行方式是复古服饰按公斤售卖。
People pick what they want and then pay according to weight rather than per item.
人们挑选好想要的衣物后，按重量而非单件付费。
Some items are upcycled – re-modelled or re-worked by adding embroidery, patches and other additions.
有些衣物还会被升级改造——通过添加刺绣、补丁和其他装饰对其进行重新设计加工。
But however these second-hand clothes are worn or re-designed, the sustainability of vintage fashion means it’s here to stay for some time to come.
但无论这些二手衣物是被直接穿着，还是经过重新设计，复古时尚的可持续性意味着它在未来一段时间内都会持续流行。